Finding Aid for Melvin R. Gilmore (1868-1940) Papers 1905-1938 and undated
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Photographs circa 1905-1930
  The Photographs series, ca. 1905-1930 (1 linear foot), provides a visual record of Gilmore's professional and personal interests. The series includes black and white prints of varying sizes, a small number of negatives and two photograph albums. More than half of the loose photos are unlabeled as to date or subject, though many also appear in the photograph albums, often with captions. The loose photographs have been arranged into broad subject groupings; there is no apparent order to the photographs within each heading, though the ordering in which they were received has been retained when possible. Ethnographic subjects include Native American people, Native American reservations and missions, medicine bundles, corn and other plants, and an Arikara fish trap. Photos of the American Ethnobotanical Garden Gilmore designed for the Museum of the American Indian can also be found in the series. In addition to photos related to his professional work, the series also includes many portraits and candid photos of Gilmore, his friends, and his professional acquaintances.
  The two photograph albums measure 6" x 4.5" and 11" x 7", respectively. Both include black and white photos, most with captions. The smaller album has a caption on the inside front cover that reads "An Album of Views Taken by M.R. Gilmore on the Omaha Indian Reservation, Northeast Nebraska" and is dated 1905 to 1906. The photos in the larger album date from 1920 to 1925 and cover an array of subjects.
  - "An Album of Views Taken by M.R. Gilmore on the Omaha Indian Reservation, Northeast Nebraska," 1905-1906 (Box 4)
  - Photograph album 1920-1925 (Box 4)
  - Loose Photographs (grouped by subject)
    - "Bismarck" (Box 5)
    - Beaver "Medicine" Omaha (Box 5)
    - Corn (Box 5)
    - Fish Trap and Arikara (Box 5)
    - Melvin R. Gilmore
      - Candids and Group Shots (Box 5)
      - Friends and Acquaintances (Box 5)
      - Portraits (Box 3)
    - Museum of the American Indian Garden 1925 (Box 5)
    - Native American Work
      - Small photographs (Box 5)
      - Medium-sized photographs (Box 3)
    - Navaho and Pueblo Corn Work (Box 5)
    - Omaha Bundles (Box 5)
    - Plants
      - Small photographs (Box 5)
      - Medium-sized photograph (Box 3)
    - St. Francis Mission, South Dakota 1924-1926 (Box 5)
    - Loose Photos from Photograph Album 1920-1925 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)